<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
    
   <P1>[Letter from <person>Marian Baldwin</person>, <date>June 30, 1917</date>]
    
    On Board <ship>La Touraine</ship>,
    
    <Date>June 30th, 1917.</Date>
    
    Even now that we are out of sight of land, it seems impossible that I am actually off to <place><country>France</country></place>
    and, for the first time in my life, traveling alone. Everything has happened so quickly since the 
    <cult>American</cult> Fund for <cult>French</cult> Wounded found an opening for me in <city><place>Paris</place></city> that I suppose I am still somewhat 
    dazed and bewildered. The fact that I don't know what it will all be like and that I can't look ahead 
    makes it easier to be happy and live in the present. Of course I have had a bit of a taste in <place><city> New York</city> </place>
    of the work that the <abrev>A. F. F. W.</abrev> is doing but its <place>Headquarters</place> in <place><city>Paris</city></place> will be different in some ways I fancy.
    
    I can't get over how lucky I am to have this chance for I realize how few <person>girls</person> of my <time>age</time>
    are getting across, and I understood the grit and pluck which made you encourage me on my great 
    adventure and send me along a path which has proved so dangerous of late.
    
    As we drifted down the <place>river</place>, in the sunset glow with two absurd <vehicle>tugs</vehicle> <action>puffing</action> alongside, 
    I know that many eyes were moist and that the same thought was in all our minds. How many 
    of this <vehicle>ship's</vehicle> company will see that sky-line again! It was very quiet, no one spoke much, 
    and, little by little, the glow <action>faded</action> from the sky and one star after another <action>appeared</action>. 
    I knew that you would be looking at those same stars down in <place>Lakewood</place> and that your thoughts
    and prayers were the same that filled my heart at that moment. Somehow distance does not separate, 
    after all.
    
    We waited near the <monument>Statue of Liberty</monument> until <time>midnight</time>—a rumor had it that a "personage" was 
    to come on board. This individual was shrouded in mystery until we put to <place>sea</place> when it was given out 
    that the party which had <action>clambered</action> aboard in the night was none other than the <cult>Italian</cult> Mission. 
    Our spirits rose at once for, what with <person>Frank Sayre</person> on the <vehicle>boat</vehicle> and these distinguished <cult>Italian</cult> gentlemen, 
    we shall doubtless be honored by a bigger convoy and so doubly safe. However, thus far we have but two 
    destroyers <action>following</action> us. They can be seen distinctly outlined against the horizon, 
    one on each side, and seem to be the same somber <color>gray</color> which all <vehicle>ships</vehicle> are <action>affecting</action> in this war. 
    A <person>sailor</person> informed me this morning that we weren't in much danger for the first four or five days 
    but that after that I might see some excitement. Here's hoping!
    
    I have a small inside <place>cabin</place> and my <person>room-mate</person> is quite a character. She is a native of 
    <place><country>Haiti</country></place>, voluble and very portly—has four large pieces of baggage in our tiny stateroom, 
    wears a costume which resembles a <person>Mother Hubbard</person> and <action>smokes</action> countless thin cigarettes that 
    <action>smell</action> like incense! When I appeared, there didn't seem to be much room for me but, as she says, 
    luckily I am small, and I was soon <action>tucked</action> into the upper berth with my belongings! She really 
    isn't bad and after <action>looking</action> me over <action>carefully</action> told me that she didn't think we would fight and 
    from that time has <action>beamed</action> upon me! She is <action>going</action> over to join her <person>son</person> who has been fighting with the 
    <cult>French</cult> since the beginning of the war but will never <action>go</action> back to the Front now, having lost some 
    fingers off each hand. She is so thankful, she says, that he hasn't <action>lost</action> more than his fingers. 
    
    [Source: _Canteening Overseas_: <date>1917-1919</date>, published <date>1920</date>.] </P1>
    
    <P2>
        
        <title>Baccarat</title>, <date>July 24th, 1918.</date>
    
   <stanza num="1"> A wonderful moon <time>to-night</time> and the countryside <action>transformed</action> under its silvery radiance. We have had terrible nights for a week now and we are all more or less worn out with little sleep and long hot days. 
    The <cult>German</cult> planes have been coming over as regularly as clock work and as this sector is unimportant compared to others farther up the line, 
    we aren't really protected at all. An English aëroplane field lies some miles in the country behind us and they do what they can to help <action>drive off</action> the enemy planes but they aren't able to <action>accomplish</action> much as they have a huge area to cover and very little equipment.
    </stanza>
        
        <stanza num="2">I thought I knew what an air raid was like after being in Paris for six months, but in comparison, those raids seem like mere child's play. 
    Ever since the moon was two days old, the <cult>Germans</cult> haven't missed a single night and as soon as it gets dark, we hear the <omin>ominous whirr</omin>. 
    At once the peace and quiet evaporate as if by magic and the whole atmosphere becomes alive with expectation and silent fears. 
    The church bell is set <action>ringing</action> furiously and the doleful sirens begin their wailing from several parts of the town at once. 
    Windows are <action>thrown</action> open and people begin to call back and forth to each other. This lasts only a few moments and then complete and utter silence. 
    Every one has gone below ground and the town lies waiting in the moonlight.</stanza>
    
    
            <stanza num="3">At first I <action>refused</action> to take refuge "dans la cave" (the cellar) partly because I didn't want to be smothered to death beneath the plaster and brick walls of the house. 
    A direct hit seemed infinitely preferable to that, also, strange as it may seem, I had no desire to get out of bed. I had lost so much sleep and had been working so hard, that night generally found me thankful for a bed. 
    Even if the noise of guns kept me awake I could rest, and the moist, <scary>chilly cellar</scary> held no charms! However, I found that staying "au lit" in the midst of an air raid was unheard of in these parts and <name>Madame M.</name> rushed into my room and with tears in her eyes implored me to accompany her below.
    The poor little old lady fears the avions above all else and the sound of their motors drives her into a frenzy of fear. In order to calm her I threw on a few clothes and we stumbled down the narrow stairs and spent the dark hours huddled in a little group around a candle that sputtered and flickered in the draughty, damp air. 
    Our party consists always of <name>Madame, Joséphine</name>, a <cult>French</cult> officer, who is likewise billeted in the house, and myself. The first night that we spent in the cellar, he was already below when we ladies arrived. I have never seen a more droll figure and I wonder now how I ever kept my face straight. 
    He was attired in pink and white pajamas and on his head at a jaunty angle sat his most dressy uniform cap covered with gold braid and pale blue broadcloth! Undoubtedly he felt it added dignity and a certain modesty to his appearance. 
    As we came down he was pacing up and down the mud floor in his bare feet! He told me that he had been through four years of war, had seen comrades blown to atoms right beside him. "I know what these bombs can do, I have seen with my two eyes, it is folly not to seek shelter in a raid, so when I hear the Boches coming, 
    I leap from my bed et je me sauve, <name>Mademoiselle</name>." I felt that he was right and that the French must be thinking some of us very children who are still taking war as a game, and looking upon our folly and daring as bravery. Surely no one has any business to waste his life. 
    For the first and perhaps the last time our lives are infinitely important and useful.</stanza>
    
    
   <stanza num="4"> This officer is really a very good sort and entertains us during the long hours with tales of all sorts. 
    We discuss the war at great length and try and keep our minds occupied and off of the terrible sounds overhead. It's great for my <cult>French</cult> and I am improving. Sometimes the noise is deafening, 
    the anti-air-craft guns keep up a continuous fire and yet the <cult>Germans</cult> don't seem to be the least bit daunted and fly just above the tops of the trees, placing their bombs with the most pitiless accuracy. 
    Last night three houses in this neighborhood were hit and in the old mill, half a block away, a young woman and her little girl were killed. It was a ghastly few hours. Madame had one fit of hysterics right after another and <action>threw</action> herself about the cellar in a spasm of fear, 
    <action>trembling</action> violently and moaning and crying. It was one of the most pathetic and terrible sights I have ever seen. We tried to quiet her but as the bombs were literally falling all about us, there wasn't much one could say to cheer her. 
    When one plane had dropped its supply of horror it would dash back and in ten minutes another would be swooping and sailing above us and the crash and uproar would begin again. In order that they may see better to do their hideous work, 
    they drop a flare which illuminates the town as though it were day. By the time the strong light has burned itself out several bombs can be neatly placed.</stanza>
    
    
    <stanza num="5">The raid generally begins about <time>nine o'clock</time> and the planes come over in rapid succession until dawn. 
    It is extraordinary what an effect the sound of the <cult>German</cult> motor has upon one. The noise even at a great distance will wake me out of a sound sleep whereas our own planes can fly right past my window and I never know it.
    This morning the town is really upset. Last night's raid was the worst yet. Two of our soldiers in the Evacuation Hospital were killed and a great number of <cult>French</cult>. 
    A bomb lit across the street from the Y and this morning I found all my canteen windows <action>smashed</action> into a thousand pieces. 
    The Boches dropped several notes all over the streets written in French which said "If you think last night's raid a bad one, wait for to-night. 
    We will break all records." The consequence is that the morale is not very good, every one worn out with no sleep, horror piled on horror, 
    and the anticipation of worse things to-night.</stanza>
    
    
   <date> Later -Same day.</date>
    
    <stanza num="6">To-day is a sizzler, quite the worse we've had. The dust pours in at the windows and the canteen is black with flies.
    We've been making lemonade for hundreds of hot, tired soldiers. They come in white with dust and the perspiration running down their <butt>cheeks</butt>. 
    No cotton uniforms to be issued this summer; the boys have to wear their woolly winter ones, poor darlings, and can't even take their blouses off. 
    The result is that if this weather continues the entire <abrev>A. E. F.</abrev> will be reduced to a grease spot!</stanza>
    
    <stanza num="7">We have <action>made</action> a hundred and sixty liters of lemonade to-day; the canteen has been jammed to the doors since early morning with men, 
    tongues hanging out and clammering for something "cold and wet." The boys stand around in a huge ring while we make the lemonade, 
    offering all kinds of advice and suggestions; I have quite a time keeping them on the other side of the counter; they all want to help but we can't 
    use more than three stalwart and professional lemon squeezers! When the huge tank is finally filled, there are loud cheers from all present and it is 
    worth anything to see the gusto with which they dispatch the lemonade down their dusty throats.</stanza>
    
    <stanza num="8">How I love this place, -it's perfectly great being attached to a division.</stanza>
    
    
    <stanza num="9"><name>Westy</name>, <name>Alice</name>, <name>Squibby</name>, who have canteens in little villages nearby, are in here quite frequently and we compare notes and discuss methods, 
    and our various problems at length. I imagine some of us will shortly be sent back to Aix as our month of change is nearing its end. 
    I can't tell you how I hate the thought of leaving, although of course I want to be where I am most needed. The simplicity of this place is a great 
    contrast to <place>Aix</place> and does appeal to me so much more than the gay whirl down there with the Casino and all its marble halls and broad terraces. 
    There the boys come and go and you do all you can to cheer them, but here they aren't on leave and are up against the real thing, and, if possible, 
    need a bit of feminine companionship more than anywhere else. Also one belongs to a unit and after a while you come to feel a very distinct sense of proprietorship, 
    your hopes and fears and special prayers are centered about the men of your outfit and their failures and successes are very much your own. O! I do hope that the Y will 
    let me stay right where I am. I have made up my mind of course to be a good soldier whatever comes, but I am hoping, hoping hard every minute that I shall be allowed to stay.
    </stanza>
        
    </P2>
    
    <P3>
       <stanza num="1"> I've been very busy to-day learning a new dance. The weekly vaudeville troop arrived from Paris minus one number and as Mr. Carrell and I have danced on several Stunt Night programs, they asked us to fill in for the missing number. 
    So we are on for a week and we were so thankful that we had something that could be put right on to fill in. This little taste of stage life under such delightful auspices, is great fun. I have a dressing room all my own, <num>No. 5</num>, and <name>Alice</name> has been an angel, 
    acts as maid and helps me change my costume between our two numbers. We are billed with the professionals all over town, "<name>Miss Baldwin</name> <name>Mr. Carrell.</name>" It looked too absurd.
    </stanza>
        
   <stanza num="2"> I come on right after the "trained cats" and, while waiting in the wings, dodge the "snake charmer's" serpents! She has two about twelve yards long apiece and they wriggle and glide around behind the stage and appear suddenly in the most unexpected manner! 
    The snake charmer keeps them between times rolled up neatly in a lunch basket with a cloth drawn tightly over the top! One of the acrobats told me she doped them. Sometimes I get so interested behind the scenes that I almost forget to go on when my turn comes. 
    These vaudeville artists are the most kind-hearted of mortals and have been so good to me and encouraged me in the nicest way the first night, telling me to "keep smiling and not be scared." One comedian has been especially good to me. 
    -He white-washes his face and wears a green nose and a suit with huge black and white checks!
   </stanza>
    
    </P3>
    
    
</root>
